I'd like to tell you a story about death and architecture.
أود أن أحكي لكم قصة عن الموت وفن العمارة.
A hundred years ago, we tended to die of infectious diseases like pneumonia,
قبل مائة سنة، اعتدنا الموت جراء أمراض معدية كالالتهاب الرئوي،
that, if they took hold, would take us away quite quickly.
حتى أنها إن استحكمت فينا، ستأخذ أرواحنا بسرعة.
We tended to die at home, in our own beds, looked after by family,
اعتدنا على الموت في المنزل، في فراشنا، في ظل رعاية العائلة،
although that was the default option
مع أن ذلك كان الخيار الافتراضي
because a lot of people lacked access to medical care.
لأن الكثير من الناس لم يتمكنوا من الحصول على الرعاية الطبية.
And then in the 20th century a lot of things changed.
ثم تغيرت الكثير من الأشياء في القرن العشرين.
We developed new medicines like penicillin
قمنا بتطوير أدوية جديدة كالبنسلين
so we could treat those infectious diseases.
كي نستطيع علاج هذه الأمراض المعدية.
New medical technologies like x-ray machines were invented.
واخترعت معدات طبية جديدة كأجهزة التصوير بالأشعة السينية.
And because they were so big and expensive,
ولأنها كانت كبيرة ومكلفة جدًا،
we needed large, centralized buildings to keep them in,
احتجنا إلى مبانٍ ضخمة ومركزية لحفظها فيها،
and they became our modern hospitals.
فأصبحت مستشفياتنا الحديثة.
After the Second World War,
وبعد الحرب العالمية الثانية،
a lot of countries set up universal healthcare systems
أقامت العديد من الدول أنظمة رعاية صحية شاملة
so that everyone who needed treatment could get it.
حتى يستطيع الجميع ممن يحتاجون العلاج الحصول عليها.
The result was that lifespans extended from about 45 at the start of the century
وكانت النتيجة ازدياد عمر السكان من حوالي 45 في بداية القرن
to almost double that today.
إلى ضعف ذلك اليوم.
The 20th century was this time of huge optimism about what science could offer,
كان القرن العشرين وقت تفاؤل عظيم بشأن ما يستطيع العلم تقديمه،
but with all of the focus on life, death was forgotten,
ولكن مع كل التركيز على الحياة، تم نسيان الموت،
even as our approach to death changed dramatically.
حتى أن طريقتنا للموت تغيرت بشكل كبير.
Now, I'm an architect,
الآن، أنا مهندسة معمارية،
and for the past year and a half I've been looking at these changes
وكنت طيلة السنة والنصف الماضية أنظر إلى هذه التغيرات
and at what they mean for architecture related to death and dying.
وإلى ما تعنينه بالنسبة لفن العمارة الذي يتصل بالموت والاحتضار.
We now tend to die of cancer and heart disease,
نحن الآن نميل إلى الموت جراء السرطان أو مرض القلب،
and what that means is that many of us will have a long period of chronic illness
وما يعنيه ذلك هو أن الكثير منا سيعانون فترة طويلة من مرض مزمن
at the end of our lives.
في نهاية حياتنا.
During that period,
وخلال تلك الفترة،
we'll likely spend a lot of time in hospitals and hospices and care homes.
من الأرجح أننا سنقضي الكثير من الوقت في المستشفيات ودور العجزة ودور الرعاية.
Now, we've all been in a modern hospital.
الآن، قد كنا جميعًا في مستشفيات حديثة.
You know those fluorescent lights and the endless corridors
تعرفون مصابيح الفلوريسنت هذه والدهاليز التي لا تنتهي
and those rows of uncomfortable chairs.
وهذه الأسطر من الكراسي غير المريحة.
Hospital architecture has earned its bad reputation.
اكتسبت عمارة المستشفيات سمعة سيئة.
But the surprising thing is, it wasn't always like this.
ولكن الشيء المدهش هو أنها لم تكن دومًا هكذا.
This is L'Ospedale degli Innocenti, built in 1419 by Brunelleschi,
هذا هو لوسبيدالي ديلي إنوشنتي الذي بُني عام 1419 على يد برونالسكي،
who was one of the most famous and influential architects of his time.
الذي كان أحد أشهر وأكثر المعماريين تأثيرًا في زمانه.
And when I look at this building and then think about hospitals today,
عندما أنظر إلى هذا المبنى ثم أفكر بشأن المستشفيات اليوم،
what amazes me is this building's ambition.
ما يدهشني هو طموح هذا المبنى.
It's just a really great building.
إنه مبنى رائع بحق.
It has these courtyards in the middle
إنه يحوي ساحات في الوسط
so that all of the rooms have daylight and fresh air,
حتى تتمتع جميع الغرف بضوء الشمس والهواء النقي،
and the rooms are big and they have high ceilings,
والغرف كبيرة وذات أسقف عالية،
so they just feel more comfortable to be in.
وبذلك فهي تكون مريحة لمن يدخلها.
And it's also beautiful.
وهي جميلة أيضًا.
Somehow, we've forgotten that that's even possible for a hospital.
بطريقة ما، فقد نسينا أن ذلك ممكن بالنسبة للمستشفيات.
Now, if we want better buildings for dying, then we have to talk about it,
الآن، إن أردنا مباني أفضل للموت، إذًا فعلينا الحديث عنها،
but because we find the subject of death uncomfortable,
ولكن لأننا نجد موضوع الموت غير مريح،
we don't talk about it,
لا نتحدث عنه،
and we don't question how we as a society approach death.
ولا نتساءل حول طريقتنا كمجتمع للموت.
One of the things that surprised me most in my research, though,
ومع ذلك، إن أحد أكثر الأشياء التي أدهشتني خلال بحثي،
is how changeable attitudes actually are.
هو مدى تغير المواقف.
This is the first crematorium in the U.K.,
هذه هي المحرقة الأولى في المملكة المتحدة،
which was built in Woking in the 1870s.
والتي بنيت في مدينة وركينغ في سبعينيات القرن السابع عشر.
And when this was first built, there were protests in the local village.
وعندما بنيت هذه لأول مرة، كانت المظاهرات تعم القرية.
Cremation wasn't socially acceptable, and 99.8 percent of people got buried.
لم تكن المحرقة مقبولة اجتماعيًا، وتم إحراق 99.8% من الناس.
And yet, only a hundred years later, three quarters of us get cremated.
وعلى الرغم من ذلك، بعد مائة سنة فقط، أحرق ثلاثة أرباعنا.
People are actually really open to changing things
الناس منفتحون حقًا تجاه تغيير الأشياء
if they're given the chance to talk about them.
لو تُركت لهم الفرصة للحديث عنها.
So this conversation about death and architecture
لذا فهذه المحادثة حول الموت وفن العمارة
was what I wanted to start when I did my first exhibition on it
كانت ما وددت البدء به عندما قمت أول معرض لي بشأنهما
in Venice in June, which was called "Death in Venice."
في مدينة البندقية في شهر يونيه، واسمه "الموت في البندقية".
It was designed to be quite playful
تم تصميم المعرض ليكون مرحًا إلى حد بعيد
so that people would literally engage with it.
لجعل الناس يتفاعلون حرفيًا معه.
This is one of our exhibits, which is an interactive map of London
هذه إحدى المعروضات، وهي خريطة تفاعلية للندن
that shows just how much of the real estate in the city
تُظهر كمية العقارات في المدينة
is given over to death and dying,
التي يتم تخصيصها للموت والاحتضار،
and as you wave your hand across the map,
وعندما تحركون أيديكم عبر الخريطة،
the name of that piece of real estate, the building or cemetery, is revealed.
ينكشف اسم قطعة العقار أو المبنى أو المحرقة هذه.
Another of our exhibits was a series of postcards
وإحدى المعروضات الأخرى كانت سلسلة من البطاقات البريدية
that people could take away with them.
يستطيع الناس أخذها معهم.
And they showed people's homes and hospitals
وقد أظهرت مساكن الناس ومستشفياتهم
and cemeteries and mortuaries,
ومحرقاتهم ومشرحاتهم،
and they tell the story of the different spaces
وهي تحكي قصة المساحات المختلفة
that we pass through on either side of death.
التي نمر بها في أي جانب من الموت.
We wanted to show that where we die
أردنا إظهار أن المكان الذي نموت فيه
is a key part of how we die.
هو جزء أساسي من كيفية موتنا.
Now, the strangest thing was the way that visitors reacted to the exhibition,
الآن، إن أغرب شيء كان ردة فعل الزوار تجاه المعرض،
especially the audio-visual works.
وخصوصًا الأعمال السمعية البصرية.
We had people dancing and running and jumping
كان لدينا أشخاص يرقصون ويركضون ويقفزون
as they tried to activate the exhibits in different ways,
كأنهم حاولوا تنشيط المعروضات بطرق مختلفة،
and at a certain point they would kind of stop
وكانوا عند مرحلة معينة يتوقفون نوعًا ما
and remember that they were in an exhibition about death,
ويتذكرون بأنهم كانوا في معرض عن الموت،
and that maybe that's not how you're supposed to act.
وأن هذه ربما لسيت الطريقة التي يفترض أن يتصرفوا بها.
But actually, I would question whether there is one way
ولكن في الحقيقة، أتساءل فيما لو كانت هناك طريقة
that you're supposed to act around death,
يمكنكم التصرف بها حول الموت،
and if there's not, I'd ask you to think about what you think a good death is,
وإن لم تكن هناك واحدة، فسأطلب منكم التفكير بشأن ما تعتقدون أنه موت جيد،
and what you think that architecture that supports a good death might be like,
وكيف ترون فن العمارة الذي يدعم الموت الجيد،
and mightn't it be a little less like this and a little more like this?
وهل يمكن أن يكون أقل شبهًا بهذا وأكثر شبهًا بهذا؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)